<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Systems on mixmix</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/tags/systems/</link><description>Recent content in Systems on mixmix</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mixmix.nz/tags/systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Power &amp; Learning</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Power &amp; Learning" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I value conciseness so here&amp;rsquo;s what I think the essence of it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; Power dynamics hamper learning
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; What a waste of potential
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id="my-history"&gt;My History
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a chance I&amp;rsquo;m wrong. Here&amp;rsquo;s my story if you want to parse it yourself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="school"&gt;School
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an inquisitive (and naive) teenager, I judged IT largely by what was offered at school.
Touch typing, some HTML maybe, but none of the really beautiful stuff.
The offering was boring and unchallenging compared to centuries-old maths and sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="university"&gt;University
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;My inquiry led me to study neuroscience, which turned out to be a bit too
reductionist to practically help me understand people (so western!). I graduated
as a mathematician, and after failing as a post-graduate research assistant
(modelling blood splatter of blunt weapon trauma), I took a government subsidy
to train as a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d really enjoyed tutoring at university, but found that my higher education on
education guided me into surprisingly unsavoury amounts of acting (playing some
authoritarian role) and crowd control (learning tricks to manipulate group
social dynamics to maintain control).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t care about the length of hair or the height of socks. Quiet (but
noticed) protest looked like attending careers day and meeting prospective
school principals in ripped jeans. I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother attending my graduation (NOTE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;going off piste often requires more paperwork later).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The irony of teaching engaging learning in a lecture format was a laugh, but the
university did introduce me to &lt;a class="link" href="https://mixmix.nz/p/unlimited" &gt;Ao Tawhiti Unlimited Discovery&lt;/a&gt; -
the only high school I would take a job at. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t an act of rebelion, more
an extension of my stubornness and pickiness (which I was rich enough to be able
to afford).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was so attractive about Unlimited was the atmosphere (or people dynamics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="radical-education"&gt;Radical Education
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/upt_learning.jpg"
width="2048"
height="1536"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/upt_learning_hu_fca6759495c5b159.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/upt_learning_hu_a24eb7aeb08f592f.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Students at Unlimited"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://mixmix.nz/p/unlimited" &gt;Unlimited&lt;/a&gt; is a state funded public secondary school that exists
because of a loophole in the law, which allowed the bending of a rule meant for
the integration of church schools into a rule which allowed the school to write
its own assessment rules. Its &amp;ldquo;special character&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;a fundamental tenet that
the child is central in directing his or her own learning so that the enthusiasm
and love of learning is retained.&amp;rdquo; My kind of place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can talk a lot about what made that environment transformative, but I think
the key was radically more equal power dynamics. As a Learning Advisor there, I
didn&amp;rsquo;t assert authority through enforcing arbitrary rules. I had conversations
on a first name-basis with people about what they cared about in life. Classes
didn&amp;rsquo;t have age-barriers, and students could choose what they wanted to do every
5 weeks. Instead of segregation and age-based hierarchy, there was conversation
and experiementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt good. People were kind (not to be confused with nice), and they learnt a
lot. Instead of negotiating bullying and claustrophobia, students spent their
time doing things like attending university level classes, running New Zealand&amp;rsquo;s
only OpenDNS server from a bedroom, and working together to support a friend
with depression. Some of the experiences moved me so deeply I still cry when I
recall them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most state education is missing the mark by a wide margin. It makes me
thoroughly sad - and angry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="art-school"&gt;Art School
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I loved Unlimited, and learnt an enourmous amount there, but I left to stretch
skills outside of teaching. There was also a massive earthquake that destroyed
the city. I moved to attend art school, where I got into programming the laser
cutter (which I was shocked to find almost no one else was using).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/laser_death_ray_2.jpg"
width="2048"
height="1536"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/laser_death_ray_2_hu_cfe1cc980fb79bfc.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/laser_death_ray_2_hu_16588743e13c6a87.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Death Ray in construction"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was the worst adult student - I know what good education looks like, and I
like giving feedback. The context and tools were great but the educators
(outside of the pure theorists) were weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left and did some relief teaching where I tried to treat students as equals. I
was horrified to discover that the acting I&amp;rsquo;d disliked in state teaching is a
two part play, and exiting a play is hard when the other actors are continually
asserting your role. Genuine conversation was overridden by a race to establish
dominance and control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="social-enterprise"&gt;Social Enterprise
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over a summer break I was introduced to Joshua Vial who taught me (and several
others) to be web developers. I took these skills and helped build Loomio (an
open source collaborative decision-making tool).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people of &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.loomio.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Loomio&lt;/a&gt; - and the garden-nebula Enspiral
within which it grew - were the next group of most excellent people I met. This
is where I was introduced more explicitly to a discourse around power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/loomio.jpeg"
width="1100"
height="885"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/loomio_hu_ad53eea31a05028b.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/loomio_hu_4df43f939f3fc979.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="124"
data-flex-basis="298px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="more-radical-education"&gt;More Radical Education
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m now a teacher at &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.devacademy.co.nz" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Enspiral Dev Academy&lt;/a&gt;, a
coding bootcamp that trains non-technical people to become junior web developers
in 9 weeks. It&amp;rsquo;s a synthesis of my interests to date - programming, learning,
and community building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take myself, and those around me to and beyond the limit of our technical
ability. The only way you can do that effectively and get anything out of it is
to be super up-front about what you do and don&amp;rsquo;t understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/eda.png"
width="820"
height="311"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/eda_hu_4fb46937b888377.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/power-and-learning/eda_hu_7aabe358ad800ca2.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="263"
data-flex-basis="632px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="power-and-knowledge"&gt;Power and Knowledge
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not knowing things for some reason brings up shame for people. The most
dangerous thing for a student is self-doubt, and sitting on shame is a good way
to get that. This is another topic I&amp;rsquo;m currently really interested in, and will
write more on some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that might be a study in itself, but I&amp;rsquo;m more interested in how &lt;em&gt;not
knowing&lt;/em&gt; plays out for teachers, because I believe this is the reason I&amp;rsquo;m not
currently an ascendant cyber-wizard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you don&amp;rsquo;t know a thing as a teacher, a &lt;strong&gt;very interesting&lt;/strong&gt; decision path
emerges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A) lie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B) admit you don&amp;rsquo;t know&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="why-would-you-lie"&gt;Why would you lie?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, if your position as teacher is predicated on your knowing more, being the
&lt;em&gt;source of truth&lt;/em&gt;, then not knowing might seem to undermine that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average high-school teacher is in a surprisingly precarious power-position -
it might look like they have control, but only through carefully guided consent
of the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a teacher in a position where their authority is coupled to their knowledge,
it is awfully appealing to steer conversation away from topics which might erode
that position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is why classes on computers suck so bad in high school - they are
born of institution, which is established in such as a way as to bind teaching
to the bounds of individual mastery, which is finite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education around computers offer a unique window into the future of learning.
The field is moving so fast, that &lt;strong&gt;the only reasonable path is to say &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t
know&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; a lot. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, then talking about new and relevant ideas won&amp;rsquo;t be
part of your curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many educational institutions, saying I don&amp;rsquo;t know is not safe for educators.
Generally they are in systems that give them positional authority to solve the
&amp;lsquo;behaviour management&amp;rsquo; problems. They are generally not afforded humanising
tools of social safety, like building genuine relationships, or sharing
vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does everyone trapped in that dynamic a huge disservice. Both teachers and
students achieve less understanding, less empathy, less collaboration, less
critical thinking, etc. The learning is poorer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="not-knowing-as-power"&gt;Not knowing as Power
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being able to say &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo; is the beginning of some fantastic cascading effects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reveals &amp;lsquo;students&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;teachers&amp;rsquo; both as learners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;opportunity to model good learning
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;critical thinking/problem solving (process over rote learning)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;asking for help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;listening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shows teacher as human, relatable
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more trust, less lying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more humanistic dynamic, better conversations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;drop shame, move to a growth mindset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go beyond boring &amp;lsquo;safe&amp;rsquo; topics
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;interesting, inspiring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;engaging (perhaps people like me 15 years ago)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;play&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how I see power dynamics hampering our learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m investing in education systems which set aside positional authority, and
foster environments in which it&amp;rsquo;s safe for everyone to be vulnerable. For older
systems, I&amp;rsquo;m building an evolving book format, designed to open education
resources and support teachers to transition from authorities to guides and
catalysts of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be working in a community which is supporting me to develop a
different sort of learning pattern for myself. Maybe if we&amp;rsquo;re lucky (and
persistent), we can shift learning patterns more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to hear from anyone else playing the long game of reshaping
education.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Uncapturable Distribution</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/galaxy.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Uncapturable Distribution" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I hang out with a bunch of big dreaming nerds with a bunch of different
interests, but when we explore what it is we want in our future, it&amp;rsquo;s a happy
thriving civilisation. You&amp;rsquo;ll know we&amp;rsquo;re there because we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking after
each other, curiously exploring, sharing our successes, and making
intergalactic friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshops were about developing a Theory of Change for each group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theory of Change&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The process of forming a &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.theoryofchange.org/what-is-theory-of-change/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Theory of
Change&lt;/a&gt; is about
coming up with a map of how change will come about in the world. It starts by
a group building a shared vision of it&amp;rsquo;s particular desired end-state is.You
then proceed to build a graph of dependent states back from that end point to
the current state of the world. This is called &amp;lsquo;back-casting&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The process has several steps including things like surfacing and testing
assumptions, detailing how you would measure successful change at each step,
and assessing the cost and nature of intervention to prgress between states.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each of the workshops, 2 hours of conversation made barely a dent in
completing a fully detailed map, but we&amp;rsquo;d revealed a lot of territory. Both
workshops explored similar veins, but here I&amp;rsquo;ll explore the second, because
it&amp;rsquo;s fresher in memory and highly relevant to my current work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-build-a-decentralised-database"&gt;Why build a decentralised database?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a workshop I ran with the Secure Scuttlebutt team who all happened to
be in San Francisco recently. Here&amp;rsquo;s what the top of our theory of change
diagram looked like :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/TOS_2.jpg"
width="309"
height="394"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/TOS_2_hu_3a42609665c5f132.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/TOS_2_hu_39717d13fba8c6bb.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="78"
data-flex-basis="188px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some important things we agreed we need to achieve were :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;specialisation without inequity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rich ecosystem (supports diverse approaches)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to explore one particular chain of states back. This format makes it
hard to simultaneously discuss the branching and interconnected dependencies,
so please forgive me if the analysis seems to narrow. I&amp;rsquo;m interested in this
particular chain because it raised questions which provided a useful frame or
lens for projects I&amp;rsquo;m working on or with. From the top it reads :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Galactic council&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large scale social harmony&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post scarcity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution primarily in service of society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution is distributed and un-ownable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We build our distribution on un-capturable technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As distribution surfaced as a theme, we tested our assumptions against real-world examples :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distribution of food and goods: supermarkets, walmart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distribution of information: email, google, facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observed that &lt;strong&gt;ownership&lt;/strong&gt; of distribution by &lt;strong&gt;actors mainly interested in
profit&lt;/strong&gt; has lead to problematic dynamics which block us from joining the
Galactic Council. See massive food waste, destruction of diversity through
monopoly, development of tools which optimise addiction and consumption,
development of tools which define value for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="some-examples"&gt;Some examples
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a breakdown of a couple of interesting cases in the context of
information distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Email]&lt;/strong&gt; : a super successful open protocol. Anyone can send emails to
anyone. The failing of email is that it has no mechanism for dealing with
un-wanted noise (see spam). This has generated a niche for organisations to
offer value (spam filtering), and capture users. For example Gmail is popular
because it does fairly reliable spam filtering. This makes email less open,
because small private servers have a harder time generating a good &amp;rsquo;not-spam&amp;rsquo;
reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distribution systems must have a solution to noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Facebook]&lt;/strong&gt; : built on an open protocol - http - but has centralised closed
databases, and a closed (proprietary) interface. Facebook&amp;rsquo;s primary motivation
is profit, which inclines it to leverage it&amp;rsquo;s closed-ness (right of refusal of
access) to extract value from it&amp;rsquo;s user-base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All parts of a distribution system need to be uncapturable - open protocols
are not sufficient&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/terms.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;facebook ToS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Google]&lt;/strong&gt; : the growth of the internet beyond easily navigable scales led to
the birth of search engines. The current winning solution to this problem is an
algorithm which determines site value based on linkages and references. Again,
this is a niche which has been captured by a primarily profit motivated
organisation. This capture looks something like a monopoly through dependence,
and is &lt;a class="link" href="http://techcrunch.com/2011/03/25/search-googles-castle-moat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;defended by a suite of related free and powerful
tools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distribution systems need to address capturable searchability&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="things-you-should-consider"&gt;Things you should consider
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve named a bunch of assumptions and principles that we think need to be
integrated in order to get us on the road to The Galactic Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is your interaction with distribution systems, are you investing in
systems that build the future you want to see?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you network online, is it via an actor interested mostly in profit?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who holds power over the definition of value of what you&amp;rsquo;re interacting with?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where do you publish your content?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s overly idealistic to transition immediately to decentralised
uncapturable solutions, but there are small choices that we can and should
start making if we want to live in a thriving society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="possible-solutions"&gt;Possible solutions
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id="open-sourcing"&gt;Open-sourcing
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/loomio.jpg"
width="1100"
height="885"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/loomio_hu_ad53eea31a05028b.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/loomio_hu_4df43f939f3fc979.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Loomio logo"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="124"
data-flex-basis="298px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.loomio.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Loomio&lt;/a&gt; (a collaborative decision-making
platform), we&amp;rsquo;ve addressed some of these same problems by a steadfast
commitment to being &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/loomio/loomio" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;. While
individual instances of the platform may have closed databases, the
open-sourcing of the platform code means that anyone can own and control their
own instance. It also makes advertising and data-mining significantly less
likely, because anyone in the community can fork the code-base and rip anything
extractive out. For Loomio this is actually a selling point - it&amp;rsquo;s a clear
signal that our primary value is in serving society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Loomio, capturing ownership has also been very seriously addressed in how
we&amp;rsquo;ve written our constitution, and our approach to investment. In short, you
can&amp;rsquo;t buy Loomio, and no one person can control it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="publish-carefully"&gt;Publish carefully
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/hypermarkdown.png"
width="81"
height="60"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/hypermarkdown_hu_2abc2a73d2aa4103.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/hypermarkdown_hu_94f93b26643c9939.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Hypermarkdown logo"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="135"
data-flex-basis="324px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might notice this isn&amp;rsquo;t published on medium. Honestly, this is an
experiment in document splicing using a tool I made currently called
&lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/mixmix/hypermarkdown" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Hypermarkdown&lt;/a&gt;. In retrospect this
approach does tick some boxes. This content is currently being hosted at
&lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/mixmix/blogposts/blob/master/uncapturable_distribution.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;
which sounds like my content might be captured buuuut, github is acutally built
on a distributed content system called &lt;a class="link" href="https://git-scm.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;. An exact
mirror of the data lives on my computer as well, and could easily be hosted by
any git based server, like a self-hosted &lt;a class="link" href="https://about.gitlab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;gitlab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s still the problem of how it is you&amp;rsquo;ve found your way to this blog.
99.9% liklihood is that in 2015 it was via facebook, or twitter (it probably
wasn&amp;rsquo;t via google because the way I built this accidentally makes it harder to
index).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Edit (2025)&lt;/strong&gt; - I&amp;rsquo;ve since pulled this into another git repo which generates
this static site using Hugo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="build-an-open-combined-protocol-database"&gt;Build an open combined protocol-database
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The solution I&amp;rsquo;m currently investing in is &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/ssbc/docs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure Scuttlebutt&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s an open and secure decentralised database
where distribution flows along trust lines, as determined by following
(positive value) and flagging (negative value).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/hermes_logo.png"
width="200"
height="200"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/hermes_logo_hu_9b6782c4307a29c9.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/uncapturable-distribution/hermes_logo_hu_cc4a8b51767480b0.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Hermes the hermit-crab"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone is free to build an app to interface (read/ write) with this database.
The first app is a proof of concept messaging app called
&lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/ssbc/patchwork" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patchwork&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out a brief introduction +&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vmQUfZMCVJ0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Scuttlebutt team is planning to open beta Patchwork in November 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overview of scuttlebutt&amp;rsquo;s solution to some know problems with distribution
systems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"&gt; All open uncapturable system: the protocol is open and the database is
open and distributed. People can only edit their own data and reference
others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"&gt; Has an uncapturable solution to noise: distribution only flows along
trust lines in the network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"&gt; Searchable: relevance is similarly determined by trust relationships in
the network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Which pitfalls have we missed?)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>