<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Disability on mixmix</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/tags/disability/</link><description>Recent content in Disability on mixmix</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mixmix.nz/tags/disability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Forecasts ⛈️ ☀️</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/p/forecasts/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mixmix.nz/p/forecasts/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/forecasts/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Forecasts ⛈️ ☀️ " /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Although this pattern emerged through the challenges of parenting, I still find
it really useful wherever there is high variability / unknowns in coordination.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="planning-with-kids-chaos"&gt;Planning with &lt;del&gt;kids&lt;/del&gt; &lt;em&gt;chaos&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I had kids, organising hang-outs went from pretty simple to something much
more unstable. For example &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s meet at the zoo at 2pm&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip; sounds easy
enough, but then toddlers don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily sleep on an exact schedule, and
there is a greater than zero chance someone could spew in the car on the way
there. Multiply these unknowns by the number of participants and it can be
pretty easy for plans to only semi-align, or totally bomb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can generate feelings that range from &lt;em&gt;mild stess&lt;/em&gt; (am I waiting for X to
arrive before we go into the zoo?) through to &lt;em&gt;total bummer&lt;/em&gt; (I was really
looking forward to an adult conversation). A particularly painful failure mode
is the &amp;ldquo;after bedtime han-gout&amp;rdquo; where no children are present (read: &lt;strong&gt;this is
my time off&lt;/strong&gt;), where some kid need arises, you are wrenched back into duty, and
your plans are cancelled. Deep expectation-reality whiplash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your plans involved other people with limited resources, you&amp;rsquo;re probably
also carrying the cost to the group in mind e.g. their expectation-reality
whiplash, and the cost of having the try to re-schedule a hang out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="decomposing-the-problem"&gt;Decomposing the problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I noticed the crux of the pain for me was the sharp divergence of reality from
expectation. Why was this happening? I think because my internal narrative was
too binary, that is only had two modes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;hangin out&lt;/code&gt; ⇒ &amp;#x1f604;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;no hangs&lt;/code&gt; ⇒ &amp;#x1f62d;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we told a story which was more nuanced&amp;hellip; reduce the surprise of the
flip between these states. Could we take in all the variables, name and
acknowledged the uncertainty, and build our story on that? Sounds like it might
be too complex, but you&amp;rsquo;ve seen this pattern before ⇒ weather forecasts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started experimenting with a friend I play
&lt;a class="link" href="https://cubecobra.com/cube/list/peach?view=spoiler" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Magic&lt;/a&gt; with. Our
conversations shifted from being more of a roller-coaster:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mix&lt;/strong&gt; : How are things looking for a game tonight? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Eric&lt;/strong&gt; : &amp;#x1f44d; Yeah I&amp;rsquo;m on! See you at 8pm &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;hellip; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Mix&lt;/strong&gt; : 😕 you coming? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Eric&lt;/strong&gt; : 👀 yep, just running a little late&amp;hellip; &lt;br /&gt;
&amp;hellip; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Eric&lt;/strong&gt; : 😔 Look I&amp;rsquo;m really sorry, I gotta cancel, child spewing&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Mix&lt;/strong&gt; : 😭 oh no! good luck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a really smooth expectation ride:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mix&lt;/strong&gt; : How are things looking for a game tonight? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Eric&lt;/strong&gt; : ☔ 30%, my youngest has a cold, stay tuned! &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Mix&lt;/strong&gt; : ❤️‍🩹 No pressure this end&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Mix&lt;/strong&gt; : ✨ Let me know if the stars align! Otherwise catch you another night&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="updated-forecast"&gt;Updated forecast
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the joys of this is that just like a weather forecast, your forecast of
the likelihood of a date working out can evolve over time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;⛈️ 40% we have quite a few &lt;a class="link" href="https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons" &gt;lemons&lt;/a&gt; on deck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;☁️ 60% grandma said she can take a kid!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;☀️ 85% sick child is asleep 🙌🤞&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want you can front-load a little context about the lemons (complexity/
challenges) that are introducing uncertainty, then subsequent updates can be really
brief, even just &amp;ldquo;20%&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast this with trying to protect people from complexity (not wanting to
prematurely complicate or worry), but then feeling pressure to offer apologies,
AND explanation, AND &lt;strong&gt;in the exact moment of some disaster unfolding&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#x1f44e;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="commitment--context"&gt;Commitment + Context
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;One thing I immediately noticed was that communicating this way separated our
commitment to the relationship from the challenges of our context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past I feel like generally people wanted to make a plan work &amp;ndash; to honour
the organising + time people have contributed, the relationship &amp;ndash; and that to
cancel plans felt like some damage that needed acknowledgement and repair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I it&amp;rsquo;s really easy for me to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x2764;&amp;#xfe0f; I would love to hang out with you! (commitment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;⛈️ 60%, here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;m working with (context)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My commitment + context can now be expressed orthogonally 🤓. It feels like it
unlocks a lot more compassion / kindness, which is especially helpful for anyone
navigating relationships intersecting with complexity, be that kids, mental
health challenges, disability etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Lemons 🍋🍋🍋</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Lemons 🍋🍋🍋" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published on Scuttlebutt in 2018. Additional section added with
updated learnings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a teacher I worked with this guy Pete Brailsford, who taught
mountaineering. He&amp;rsquo;d take students up into the snow and build snow caves to
sleep in overnight, cross rivers, stuff like that. A major part of the learning
in that context was about &lt;em&gt;managing risks&lt;/em&gt;. The idea is that you can&amp;rsquo;t control
everything, but you can keep an eye on the probability field you&amp;rsquo;re standing
in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/pete_tramping.jpeg"
width="944"
height="693"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/pete_tramping_hu_85ecbd277aac1cef.webp 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/pete_tramping_hu_ea1aab21318a24f8.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Pete Brailsford Tramping"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="136"
data-flex-basis="326px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He talked about it like a slot machine - those ones where you pull the handle
and then the options spin and then they lock in like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="cherries-lemon-cherries-cherries-green_apple"&gt;&amp;#x1f352; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f352; &amp;#x1f352; &amp;#x1f34f;
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Normally if you get all cherries or something, it&amp;rsquo;s a jackpot, but in this
story, if you get a row of lemons, that&amp;rsquo;s bad, like &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you got hypothermia and
no-one knows where you are&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you can&amp;rsquo;t control all the slots, but you can watch where you&amp;rsquo;re at. Say you
set out on our adventure, the slots are spinning, and you know what, someone in
our group forgot their jacket &lt;em&gt;BOOM&lt;/em&gt; the first slot just came up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="lemon-white_large_square-white_large_square-white_large_square-white_large_square"&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c;
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ok it&amp;rsquo;s a lemon, but no big deal, it&amp;rsquo;s sunny as. You stop and have lunch,
there&amp;rsquo;s some clouds on the horizon, but it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;so warm&lt;/em&gt;. Guess what you just
missed a hint, and as you continue to walk it starts to rain and a wind picks
up (being a small island in a massive ocean, weather can change &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; quickly
in nz) &amp;hellip; now you&amp;rsquo;ve got 2 lemons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="lemon-lemon-white_large_square-white_large_square-white_large_square"&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c;
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Again this is not that big a deal&amp;hellip; except you already have that 1 lemon, so
now you&amp;rsquo;ve got someone in your group who&amp;rsquo;s getting cold. I guess you can see the
trend. Any one of these things is no big deal, but a series of little
misfortunes have a &lt;em&gt;cumulative&lt;/em&gt; effect in terms of the odds you&amp;rsquo;re playing
with. So if you&amp;rsquo;re in this position&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="lemon-lemon-lemon-lemon-white_large_square"&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x2b1c;
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re now playing a very high stakes games, where one more little lemon, like a
sprained ankle can tip you over into disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-to-manage-lemons"&gt;How to manage lemons
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lemons aren&amp;rsquo;t always avoidable, but you can often plan ahead and consider what
the odds of lemons are based on different paths. Further, you can reflect as
situtations evolve, asking yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many lemons are we currently at?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just having this self-reflective question in your toolbelt can change how you
think and see. It can be really hard to spot them because they can often be
innocuous in the context where they first present &amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s just &lt;em&gt;in concert&lt;/em&gt;
that the the real trouble manifests. Asking this question out loud to yourself
and your questing party can help you spot more of them early, as well as
increase the liklihood you&amp;rsquo;ll keep them in working memory (most humans suck at
remembering many small factors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you spot yourself crossing 3-4 lemons, you should probably be starting to
significantly re-asses your plans. Things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;abort&lt;/strong&gt;: ask yourself if your initial plan is still safe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;simplify&lt;/strong&gt;: consider cutting non-vital parts of your plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;alert&lt;/strong&gt;: increase new-lemon vigilance, prepare to escalate responses faster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="but-mix-im-not-a-mountaineer"&gt;But mix, I&amp;rsquo;m not a mountaineer
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is relevant to anyone on any adventure (solo, or as a team). You could be
voyaging into literal mountains, or sailing to Great Barrier Island, or you could
be a distributed team building FOSS tools on a limited / no budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some lemons that have fucked up quests I&amp;rsquo;ve been on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having no retrospectives (process for iterating, adaptation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;just trusting that everyone remembers the agreement we made &lt;em&gt;(contracts, pay,
expectations)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;forgetting to ask how people are feeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;figuring it out later&amp;rdquo; for on-boarding / off-boarding / holidays / sick leave&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not telling each other vital quest-changing info &lt;em&gt;(assuming mind-reading or
avoiding conflict)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being unclear on who&amp;rsquo;s doing what&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using too many different tools for communication / coordination&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being unclear about ownership / responsibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;saying &amp;ldquo;this is a flat structure, everyone is equal&amp;rdquo; (but not actually doing
anything to actively distribute power)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;forgetting to account for how disruptive travel can be&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the course you take has known lemons. Like it&amp;rsquo;s hard to set up
&lt;em&gt;holiday pay&lt;/em&gt; processes when you&amp;rsquo;re a small company and you know everyone and
you&amp;rsquo;re doing it for love and there are so many things to do. You just need to
acknowledge (and remember) that you&amp;rsquo;re carrying a lemon, and if you then try to
onboard someone new, you need to adjust your plan by either stopping to build
that missing stuff (unloading the lemon), or communicating to the new person
clearly about the known lemon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lemons-in-family-systems"&gt;Lemons in family systems
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added this section because it&amp;rsquo;s how I&amp;rsquo;ve most used this
personally, and why I reference this pattern so often.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say &amp;ldquo;family system&amp;rdquo;, I mean any group of people very strongly committed
to supporting one another, such that the wellbeing of any one person in the
system &lt;em&gt;strongly&lt;/em&gt; effects the wellbeing of the system as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of family systems I&amp;rsquo;ve seen that this is relevant for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parent(s) with kid(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;partners where at least one has a disability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;partners where at least one has mental health challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know if you&amp;rsquo;re in such a family system when e.g. one of you gets sick, and
the experience is like &lt;em&gt;the family is sick&lt;/em&gt;. The arc of recovery is often slower
too, because of the complex interactions involved in one person getting taken
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="noticing-lemons"&gt;Noticing lemons
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t track lemons all the time in our family. Lemons in themselves are not
bad &amp;hellip; unattended compounding lemons tend towards disaster though. Typically we
start engaging this pattern when we notice ourselves generally &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;unreasonably&lt;/em&gt; stressed&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;a bit&lt;/em&gt; overwhelmed&amp;rdquo;, or even just &amp;ldquo;unproductive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to &lt;strong&gt;pause&lt;/strong&gt; and name the lemons we can spot. I&amp;rsquo;m feeling a bit
overwhelmed today, so here&amp;rsquo;s an example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; work &amp;ndash; my work is in transition, lots of uncertainty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; community &amp;ndash; my school picnic got quagmired, lots of painful learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; health &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve had a low level cold for 2 weeks, have had a few nights
of bad sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okeee, so we&amp;rsquo;re at 3 lemons already, and that&amp;rsquo;s only counting the complexities
I&amp;rsquo;m holding&amp;hellip; No wonder I&amp;rsquo;m feeling a bit overwhelmed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="compassion"&gt;Compassion
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even noticing that you&amp;rsquo;ve carrying a bunch of lemons can be transformative. My
first step is usually to laugh a little, and feel a little bit of relief &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m
not useless, we have a lot on!&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#x1f605;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having some compassion for ourselves can immediately unload shame / guilt /
pressure, which is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; strategic, because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you just cut a meta-lemon (wasting brain cycles beating yourself up)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you likely have less of a white-knuckle death-grip on your initial plans,
making it easier to adapt to your actual reality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="complexity-capacity-lemon-spoon"&gt;Complexity capacity &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f944;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another pattern we use in our family is &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spoon_theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Spoon
Theory&lt;/a&gt;. The core idea is that if
you&amp;rsquo;re living with some disability you may have very limited capacity, and that
we could model how much capacity people have with units of capacity, spoons
&amp;#x1f944; say. A person with very limited capacity might start the day with 8
spoons, and then have to ration their spoons over the day e.g. shower costs 1
spoon, commute to work costs 2 spoons etc). If you run out of spoons&amp;hellip; maybe
you cannot get home, maybe you can but end up in massive spoon-debt (goodbye
tmrw).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expanding spoons from the individual (to collective capacity) and blending in
the lemons pattern, we can start to say things like &amp;ldquo;today we only have capacity
for 2 lemons&amp;rdquo;. Lemons here represent complexity which will incur spoons
(capacity) cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feels kind because it acknowledges our current capacity, and helps us bound
expectations of how much complexity we can perhaps carry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concretely, while going to a kids birthday in the morning followed by a friends bbq
in the afternoon may seem easy, if we only have 4 spoons, and
this plan takes us to 0 spoon exactly&amp;hellip; that leaves no capacity for unforeseen
lemons, which world put us in spoon deficit. Better to plan one just the one
activity and have spare capacity for curveballs and still be within safe
operating bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This concept is also useful in the context of startups. Startups are typically
operating with very limited resources (spoons). Basic operations cost capacity
(spoons), and innovation tends to cost in unforeseen complexity (lemons). To that
end it&amp;rsquo;s important not to innovate on too many fronts simultaneously. Examples of
things which incur complexity cost:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;ldquo;fancy&amp;rdquo; legal structures - e.g. coop, foundation + for-profit symbiosis, &amp;hellip;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; novel technologies - e.g. encrypted replicatable database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; ethical investment mechanisms - e.g. non-voting shares, redeemable preference shares, &amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#x1f34b; world-spanning teams - e.g. NZ, EU, USA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>